Unity engine is an incredibly popular
video game and 3D engine that is used by
tons and tons of mobile and desktop
games like Among Us or Fall Guys among
many many others are made using Unity
the unity engine is so popular that is
calculated that 70 of all mobile games
are built on Unity it also has a huge
online community that is full of
tutorials courses forums YouTube
channels and books it's also very
popular among Indie developers and
students because it uses an easy to
learn programming language C sharp but
the most important thing is free to get
started with if a game makes less than
one hundred thousand dollars a year
which is the case for most students
hobbyists and Indie developers the
personal license of the unity engine is
absolutely free if a game makes more
than that or if the developers want to
deploy the game on consoles like
Nintendo switch PlayStation and Xbox
they will need to get a pro license that
is around two thousand dollars a year
it's a flat fee so for example if you
made a game with unity and sold it and
made 10 million dollars your only cost
will be the license the two thousand
dollars if you build the same game with
Unreal Engine another 3D engine the
license would be free but you will have
to pay them five percent after your
first million dollars five percent of 9
million is more than 400 Grand so it's
easy to see why the pricing of unity was
so attractive for so many people and why
it is so popular Unity has been very
generous for a long time but as it was
announced on September 12th that is
going to change and that is the reason
why so many game developers from Big to
small companies are outraged with unity
this has got to be one of the worst
price changes in history and it's not
even about money it's about trust and
how Unity broke it which is why it's
going to be so hard for them to recover
from this even if they do a complete
U-turn and cancel their plan price
changes happen all the time and most
people understand that companies need to
make money Unity is an amazing product
and it's understandable that they need
money to keep developing it and to keep
the light on so the problem isn't that
the price is changing it is the way it
is changing and how this connected the
management of unity is from the
developer Community people that spend
Years Learning the software and building
businesses that rely on Unity are
feeling like The Rock was pulled from
underneath them and are feeling totally
betrayed it is a mess hundreds of game
studios including some of the big guys
have announced that they will be
switching to another game engine and
have made public statements on how bad
this change is so let's unpack the price
change as well as the events that
followed to understand how big of a
catastrophe this is on the opening
paragraph of the announcement the
company wrote that the unity engine is
actually two pieces of software one is
the editor where you make the game and
another one is the unity runtime the
unity runtime is the wrapper that makes
it possible for your game to work on
Xbox PlayStation IOS and Android it
wraps your game and your code and it
makes sure that it can be run on any
platform including the web and that is
what Unity wants to start charging for
they will now charge Unity runtime fee
where developers will have to start
paying per install which is insane here
is a table that calculates how much a
game would pay so let's pretend we are a
small in the depth first let's check
eligibility we will have to pay this fee
if and only if our game made more than
200 Grand on the last 12 months and if
our game has been installed more than
000 times if any of those conditions is
not met we don't have to pay a thing but
if both of those things are true then we
will have to pay 20 cents per install at
a first glance it seems reasonable since
most games will not hit those thresholds
but at a Second Glance this pricing is
actually horrible for mobile games and
it could end up on us going bankrupt
most mobile games are free and they have
either ads or in-app purchases ads don't
pay that much and not everyone that
plays the game spends money on in-app
purchases so let's say that we make a
game that goes viral with 2 million
downloads and we managed to make 250 000
of in-app purchases that means we will
hit both thresholds and have to to pay
the fee paying 20 cents for one million
800 000 installations since the first
two hundred thousand are free will mean
that we now owe Unity 360
000 when we only made 250 000 on the
first place we have to give unity all
the money we made with in-app purchases
plus more money from our own pocket we
will end up losing money because our
game went viral in contrast if we made
that same game with Unreal Engine we
would not have to pay a thing and it
gets even worse if we think about
computer games you could say these
pricing sort of works for computer games
where if you are above the threshold and
let's say your game is 30 bucks giving
20 cents doesn't seem like a big cut but
still charging per install is a horrible
idea because it leaves the door open for
Bad actors to attack in bankrupt game
developers people could literally
coordinate attacks to install your game
out of Sprite to cost you money and even
worse if the game is pirated the
developer will still have to pay every
time a copy of the stolen game is is
installed so now the question is how are
installs going to be tracked will app
stores do it or steam no Unity
themselves will count the installs using
what they call a proprietary data model
they're basically saying trust us we
will know how much to charge you and we
will be accurate when asked questions
about reinstalls the company said that
reinstalled on the same device will not
come if that is true that means I will
have to collect identifiable information
of the player's device which might be a
privacy violation in places like Europe
they did clarify that if a user installs
your game in two separate devices maybe
because they change their computer you
will have to pay the installation fee
twice if that sounds bad it gets even
worse you could make the case that Unity
is a private company and they have the
right to change the price going forward
and if they gave sufficient notice game
studios could have time to choose to
release in new games using Unity or go
to another engine for their next games
the problem and what makes this price
change so incredibly bad is that it will
not only apply for new games made after
the price change Unity has decided to
apply These Chains retroactively that
means for games that are already
released games that were made years ago
will have to start paying the runtime
fee imagine that you pay for a Photoshop
license years ago and well into the
future Adobe decides that you have to
start paying them money for all the
photos you make with Photoshop and all
the photos you made 10 years ago
changing the terms and conditions
retroactively is such a mean move and as
some people have pointed out it might
not be entirely illegal drugs takes
years to build seconds to break and
forever to repair and unity has broken
the trust of developers it has shown
what they can do and how far they will
go to charge developers more money after
a week of announcing the price change
Unity seems to finally be listening and
they have announced they will be making
changes to the policy after talking to
their team Community customers and
partners even if they do a complete
U-turn and cancel their plans a hundred
percent the trust is gone who is going
to build a game Studio that relies on
Unity again in how can game developers
trust that Unity won't try to do this
again in the future the creator of
Gary's mod and the rust game said it
best in a blog post titled Unity can get
he says we used the engine
because you pay up front and then ship
your product we have spent 10 years
making rust on unity's engine we have
paid them every year and now they change
the rule he says the trust is gone and
that Rost 2 will definitely not be a
unity game it is really hard to tell
what happens right now even if Unity
changes the policy and allows game
developers themselves to self-report
installations that is just giving
developers a new job to do track and
install even if they lower the fee it is
a new fee that did not existed before
that many people see as unfair anyways
or if they make the thresholds higher
that will still mean that it will be
scary as a game developer to succeed
when using Unity 3D many people are
saying that by doing this Unity has
single-handedly given Victory 2 Unreal
Engine an engine with just a five
percent fee no thresholds installed all
tracking tiers licenses Etc also this is
a super win for open source engines like
Godot where many developers of the unity
cam are moving too overall I feel sorry
for the people working with unity it
must feel incredibly infuriating to go
through something like this I also feel
sorry for the people that published
courses or tutorials and they voted lots
of time to teaching and learning a
software that became almost radioactive
for the game industry overnight all the
people that were in the middle of making
a game in unity will they finish and
release the game or will they have to
move to a different engine and refactor
the game completely what a nightmare I
want to know what you think on the
comments let me know what your opinion
is of all this and let me know after
everything that has happened if you
would still trust Unity even if they do
a complete U-turn and cancel their plans
I don't know if I could companies should
not take Developers for granted no one
likes it when you mix with their
livelihoods if a tool is not reliable
developers will find a different better
one I hope you liked the video and found
it informative and useful if you did
please like the video share it with your
friends and subscribe to the Channel
please don't forget that if you want to
learn to code for free all you have to
do is click the link below where you can
take free courses on JavaScript python
react react native go dark flutter
next.js and many others all for free
click the link below and I will see you
there
see you on the next one bye
foreign